Theodor Reik Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Theodor Reik Papers 1905-1994 1939-1969
MSS86021
Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969
7,500 items
18 containers plus 7 oversize
12 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst and author. Correspondence, interviews, family papers, handwritten and some typed drafts of books and other writings, reprints of journal articles, notes, research files, certificates, publishing contracts, royalty statements, reviews of Reik's books, publicity materials, photographs, honors and a tribute, brochures, programs, postcards, and news clippings documenting Reik's contributions to psychoanalytic theory and practice, largely through his prolific writing for professional and popular audiences.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Abraham, Karl, 1877-1925.; Adler, Guido, 1855-1941.; Eissler, K. R. (Kurt Robert), 1908-1999--Correspondence.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Graf, Max, 1873-1958.; Mahler, Gustav, 1860-1911.; Meerloo, Joost Abraham Maurits, 1903-1976--Correspondence.; Nydes, Jule, 1911-1967--Correspondence.; Pais, Abraham, 1918-2000--Correspondence.; Reik family.; Reik, Arthur, 1915-1988.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. Jewish wit. 1962.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. Many faces of sex. 1966.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. Need to be loved. 1963.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. Of love and lust. 1949.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. Pagan rites in Judaism: from sex initiation, magic, moon-cult, tattooing, mutilation, and other primitive rituals to family loyalty and solidarity. 1964.; Reik, Theodor, 1888-1969. The haunting melody; psychoanalytic experiences in life and music. 1953.; Rosé, Arnold, 1863-1946.; Walter, Bruno, 1876-1962.
Subjects
Couvade.; Guilt.; Humor.; Jewish wit and humor.; Judaism--Customs and practices.; Judaism--Relations.; Judaism.; Lay analysis (Psychoanalysis); Love--Psychological aspects.; Lust--Psychological aspects.; Man-woman relationships--United States--20th century.; Man-woman relationships.; Marriage.; Masochism.; Men--Psychology.; Psychoanalysis--Austria.; Psychoanalysis--Germany.; Psychoanalysis--Netherlands.; Psychoanalysis--Practice.; Psychoanalysis--Research.; Psychoanalysis--United States.; Psychoanalysis.; Puberty rites.; Sex (Psychology); Sex customs.; Sex differences (Psychology); Women--California--Social life and customs.; Women--New York (State)--New York--Social life and customs.; Women--Psychology.; World War, 1939-1945--Women--New York (State)--New York.
Places
Palestine--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Emigration and immigration.; United States--Intellectual life--20th century.; United States--Social conditions--20th century.; United States--Social life and customs--20th century.
Occupations
Authors.; Psychoanalysts.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Theodor Reik, psychoanalyst and author, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 2015.
Transfers
Audio recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Theodor Reik Papers.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the Sigmund Freud Papers which contain Reik's correspondence with Freud and a separate Theodor Reik Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Theodor Reik are open to research. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1888, May 12 Born, Vienna, Austria
1910 Completed undergraduate studies in psychology and literature, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria Met Sigmund Freud
1911 Admitted to the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society
1912 PhD, University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria
1914 Married Eleanore (“Ella”) Oratsch (died 1934) Moved to Berlin, Germany, to begin analysis with Karl Abraham Received the first award in applied psychoanalysis for his essay “The Puberty Rites of Savages,” Imago, vol. 4 (1915): 189-222
1915 1918 Served in World War I
1918 Returned to Vienna, Austria
1928 Moved to Berlin, Germany
1934 Moved to The Hague, Netherlands Married Marija Cubelic (died 1960)
1938 Immigrated to the United States, settling in New York, N.Y.
1944 Became a United States citizen
1948 Founded the National Psychological Association for Psychoanalysts
1953 Published The Haunting Melody (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Young)
1957 Published Of Love and Lust: On the Psychoanalysis of Romantic and Sexual Emotions (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Giroux)
1962 Published Jewish Wit (New York: Gamut Press)
1963 Published The Need to Be Loved (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Co.)
1964 Published Pagan Rites in Judaism (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Co.)
1966 Published The Many Faces of Sex (New York: Farrar, Straus, and Giroux)
1969, Dec. 31 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Theodor Reik (1888-1969) span the years 1905-1994, with the bulk of the material dating from 1939 to 1969. The collection documents Reik's contributions to psychoanalytic theory and practice as a lay analyst and researcher, and as one of Sigmund Freud's first students. The papers date largely after Reik's immigration to the United States in 1938, but also include material from his earlier years in Austria, Germany, and the Netherlands. Much of the collection focuses on Reik's prolific writing for both professional and popular audiences. Many of these works explore Reik's theories on the psychological differences between men and women and were published as gender relations were being transformed in the postwar years. Included are partial drafts of many of Reik's books, reprints and copies of his published articles, notes, and research files, as well as correspondence, publishing contracts, royalty statements, certificates, interviews, photographs, and news clippings. The collection is in English and German, with English predominating after 1938. It is arranged in four series: Personal and Family Papers, Gustav Mahler, Writings File, and Oversize.
The Personal and Family Papers series contains material from Reik's personal files as well as those of his son Arthur Reik who served as his father's literary agent and later as the literary executor for his estate. The series represents a small portion of what must have once comprised Reik's personal files, but nevertheless provides insights into his career and the reception of his work, particularly in the United States. Highlights of the series include correspondence from colleagues, publishers, and readers of Reik's books; royalty statements; book reviews and publicity materials about his books; oral history interview transcripts; and newspaper articles about him. Also included are certificates, 1908-1912, from Reik's studies at the University of Vienna.
The Gustav Mahler series is the most intact portion of the collection and consists of Reik's research and writings on the composer's life and work. Included are concert programs, journal articles, booklets, and news clippings about Mahler and performances of his works, some dating from the 1920s and 1930s, as well as Reik's research notes and drafts of his writings. Among these writings are an article on Sigmund Freud's analysis of the composer and a file of handwritten draft manuscripts in German that eventually became The Haunting Melody: Psychoanalytic Experiences in Life and Music (1953), Reik's book on Mahler that explores the nature of musical associations.
The Writings File is the largest series in the collection and includes drafts of some of Reik's books, articles, introductions, and speeches; printed copies of his journal, newspaper, and magazine articles; three notebooks; and a large volume of notes. Reik wrote in English and German, switching largely to English after 1938. Copies of Reik's published articles and commentary span his publishing career from 1911 to 1968. The series' book files, however, date largely after his immigration to the United States and focus in particular on his writings on Judaism and gender relations. The surviving book drafts and notes suggest several ways Reik emulated his mentor Sigmund Freud's approach to writing. Reik, like Freud, preferred to compose on large sheets of paper. Many of Reik's writings, therefore, are stored in the Oversize series. Also like Freud, Reik showed an apparent disregard for his drafts and notes after a work was published. Reik's writing files arrived at the Library minimally organized and described and in poor physical condition. Yet most of the bundles of otherwise unidentified drafts and notes seemed to have distinct focuses, making it possible to associate them with specific writing projects. Even so, many of the books in the collection are only partially documented, at times with no more than several pages or a single chapter. Exceptions are Reik's books Jewish Wit and Pagan Rites in Judaism which have more complete drafts and The Many Faces of Sex, The Need to Be Loved, and Part IV in Of Love and Lust on Reik's theories regarding the emotional differences between men and women. Files for these latter three books consist of randomly organized notes and partial drafts rather than complete manuscripts. The large volume of notes stored in the book files and in separately organized note files capture the unfolding of Reik's thought process. According to Reik, he would record his thoughts, insights, and observations in note form, often in the evenings after a full day of seeing patients. The first drafts of his books grew out of these notes. Also included in the series are writings by others. Some of these article-length works explore Reik's contributions to psychoanalysis. Also included are writings by two women who, at one time, may have been Reik's analysands.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Personal and Family Papers, 1908-1984
Gustav Mahler, 1905-1994
Writings File, 1911-1994
Oversize, 1911-1962
Container List
- Personal and Family Papers, 1908-1984 (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence, interviews, certificates, publishing contracts, royalty statements, reviews of Reik's books, publicity materials, a tribute on his seventieth birthday, brochures, programs, a photograph, postcards, and news clippings from the personal files of Reik as well as those of his son Arthur who served as Reik's literary agent and later as the literary executor for his estate. Most of the material in the series dates after Reik's immigration to the United States and, although not extensive, sheds light on Reik's contributions to the growing popularity of psychoanalysis in postwar America. A small general correspondence file focuses largely on Reik's research and writing and includes several letters from colleagues, among them psychoanalysts K. R. Eissler, Joost Abraham Maurits Meerloo, and Jule Nydes. Also included are letters, some with extensive commentary, from people who read Reik's books. Among these is a letter from novelist Herbert Gold on Psychology of Sex Relations which Gold read in 1945 while serving in the army at Camp Albert C. Ritchie, Maryland. Other correspondents include physicist Abraham Pais. Posthumous correspondence is addressed to Arthur Reik and includes condolence letters on Reik's death in 1969, letters from scholars about Reik's work, and correspondence about Arthur's interest in Gustav Mahler which he shared with his father. The reception of Reik's work can be traced through book contracts and correspondence with publishers, royalty statements, book reviews, and news articles about him.
  Reik's life in Europe before his immigration is documented through certificates from his studies at the University of Vienna; newspaper articles, 1913-1938, about or referring to him; and later interviews with Reik in which he discussed his family and childhood, studies at the University of Vienna, relationship with Sigmund Freud, analysis with Karl Abraham, controversies surrounding lay analysis, his research and writing on psychoanalysis, and other aspects of his life and work. A small amount of family papers includes his first wife Eleanore Oratsch Reik's residential certificate in 1915, a copy of Arthur Reik's 1936 marriage certificate, and letters from Reik to his son in 1939-1941 urging his immigration to the United States from Palestine.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
  - Audio recordings, information concerning, 1952, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Books by Reik (Box 1)
    - Publicity and two dust jackets, 1935-1964 (Box 1)
    - Reviews, 1919-1976, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Certificates (Box 1)
    - Reik, Arthur (son), marriage, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Reik, Eleanore Oratsch (wife), residential and passport, 1915, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Reik, Theodor (Box 1)
      - Honors, 1960-1968 (Box 1)
      - New York State psychologist certificate, 1959 See Container OV 1, Certificate (Box 1)
      - University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria, 1908-1912 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - General, 1935-1979, undated, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - With publishers, including contracts, 1940-1965, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - With publishers, including contracts, 1966-1984, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Executor of estate, release, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Interviews with Reik by (Box 2)
    - Delafield, [?], 1945 (Box 2)
    - Eissler, K. R., 1954 (Box 2)
    - Freeman, Erika Padan, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Swerdloff, Bluma, Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1932-1954 (Box 2)
  - National Psychological Association for Psychoanalysts (Box 2)
    - General, 1952-1962, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Theodor Reik Clinic for Mental Health and Research, New York, N.Y., 1955-1962 (Box 2)
  - News clippings and other printed matter (Box 2)
    - Annotated by Reik, "Die Zukunfteiner Illusion," by Sigmund Freud, pp. 81-91, 1927 (Box 2)
    - Mentioning Reik, 1913-1970 (Box 2)
    - Saved by Reik, 1908-1930s, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Saved by Reik, 1940s-1962, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Photograph of a woman and a man, undated (Box 3)
  - Postcards, ancient Egyptian and medieval European art, undated (Box 3)
  - Programs, miscellaneous, 1956-1977, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Royalties (Box 3)
    - Notes, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Statements, 1951-1952, 1969-1982, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Speaking engagement notices, 1939, 1958-1962 (Box 3)
  - Tribute on seventieth birthday, 1958 (Box 3)
- Gustav Mahler, 1905-1994 (Box 3-7)
  Drafts of writings, notes, photographs, and collected printed matter consisting of newspaper clippings, concert programs, journal articles, and booklets stemming from Reik's research and writings on Gustav Mahler. Reik's research on the composer stretched over many years, beginning before his immigration in 1938 and culminating in the publication of The Haunting Melody: Psychoanalytic Experiences in Life and Music in 1953. Included in the series is a set of five binders containing notes, drafts, printed matter, and photographs stored in topically labeled folders. The contents of Binder A focuses largely on Mahler's biography, commemorations of the seventy-fifth anniversary of his birth and twenty-fifth anniversary of his death in 1935-1936, and writings about the composer by Guido Adler, Max Graf, Arnold Rosé, and Bruno Walter, among others. Binder B covers a wide variety of topics, including anecdotes about Mahler, his relationships with Hans von Bülow and Sigmund Freud, his religious and superstitious inclinations, his years in Vienna, and a planned memorial. Files on Mahler's symphonies and other compositions are housed in Binder C. Binders D and E contain Reik's notes on Mahler which he taped to numbered sheets. The tape has been removed, but the original order of the notes has been maintained. In addition to the binders, the series includes loose notes and drafts, largely in German, and additional printed matter including booklets, journals, reprints, catalogs, concert programs, news clippings, and a facsimile edition of Mahler's Symphony no. 10.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Binders See also Containers OV 1-OV 2, same heading (Box 3)
    - Binder A, 1928-1963, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Binder A, 1928-1963, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Binder B, 1912-1954, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Binder C, 1905-1955, (4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Binder D, notes 1-12, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Binder D, notes 13-31, undated, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Binder E, notes 32-51, undated, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Binder E, notes 52-70, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Loose handwritten notes and drafts, largely in German, undated See also Container OV 2, same heading, (9 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1959-1981, undated (Box 6)
  - Portrait drawings, bronze bust, and death mask, copies of, undated See also Container OV 2, Copy of a portrait (Box 6)
  - Printed matter (Box 6)
    - Booklets, journals, and reprints, 1905, 1920-1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Catalogs and a directory, undated (Box 7)
    - Concert programs, New York Philharmonic, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - Facsimile edition of Mahler's Symphony no. 10, 1924 See Container OV 2, same heading (Box 7)
    - News clippings, 1936-1984 (Box 7)
- Writings File, 1911-1994 (Box 7-18)
  Handwritten notes, notebooks, and German and English manuscripts, handwritten and typed drafts of books and articles, copies of articles published in journals and magazines, two speeches, introductions to works by others, and a file of writings by others. Like his mentor Sigmund Freud, Reik often wrote on large sheets of paper so a significant portion of the series is stored in the Oversize series. Some of the oversize material is in fragile condition and should be handled with care.
  The Writings File, with its collection of notes, early drafts, and, in some cases, near-complete book drafts, reflects Reik's writing process. Reik wrote notes on scraps of paper and grouped them into packets by topic, most numerously on Judaism and the relationship between men and women. These original groupings have been retained and are identified by the topical headings created by Reik. The notes consist largely of Reik's own reflections and observations as well as insights gleaned from psychoanalytic sessions and his readings. The topics discussed in the unidentified manuscript pages mirror those found in the note packets, with a majority of the pages focusing on the relationship between men and women. Many of these unidentified handwritten pages have no title, page number, or other identifying characteristics that might tie them to a particular article or book of Reik's, and so have been separated by language and then grouped into sets based on the original order as received. Identified manuscript drafts of books and articles are sorted by title; however, even when identified, a majority of the book drafts are incomplete and some contain only a few miscellaneous pages.
  While most of the material in the series was generated after Reik's immigration to the United States in 1938 and before his death in 1969, some newspapers, magazines, and journal articles as well as writings by others extend before and after those dates. Reik began writing literary and general articles for Viennese newspapers and magazines soon after completing his doctorate in 1912, and continued publishing in newspapers and magazines after his immigration. Included in the collection is a series of articles on “Men, Women and Love” published in the New York Herald Tribune in 1958. Other topics covered in his magazine and journal articles include couvade, gender relations, guilt, humor, masochism, and puberty rites. Some of the newspaper and magazine articles are in very poor physical condition and have been photocopied for ease of use.
  The file of writings by others includes article-length drafts and reprints, some of which pertain to Reik or topics of interest to him. Also included in the file are journal-like letters and manuscripts by two women who may have been Reik's analysands. Barbara Ivins' writings contain the reflections of a young woman living in wartime New York in 1944. Dorothy Jeffery's letters and manuscripts, written in 1954, discuss her thoughts on the relation between men and women, her marriage, and life in California.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein by title of topic.
  - By Reik (Box 7)
    - Book drafts and notes (Box 7)
      - Curiosities of the Self, miscellaneous pages, circa 1965 (Box 7)
      - Fragment of a Great Confession, "Roads of Destiny," circa 1949 (Box 7)
      - From Thirty Years with Freud, "Das Echo des Sprichwörtes," circa 1940 (Box 7)
      - The Haunting Melody, "Aria Without Words" ("Three Women in a Man's Life"), circa 1953 See Container OV 3, Handwritten and typed drafts (Box 7)
      - Jewish Wit, circa 1962 (Box 7)
        - Handwritten drafts and notes on large sheets See Container OV 3, same heading (Box 7)
        - Typescript, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - The Many Faces of Sex, circa 1966, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - The Many Faces of Sex, circa 1966, (4 folders) (Box 8)
      - Masochism in Modern Man, miscellaneous pages, circa 1941 (Box 8)
      - Myth and Guilt, preface and outline, circa 1957 See Container OV 3, Preface (Box 8)
      - The Need to Be Loved, circa 1963, (9 folders) (Box 8)
      - Of Love and Lust, circa 1957 (Box 8)
        - Part III, chapter titled "The Chip on the Shoulder" See Container OV 4, Handwritten draft (Box 8)
        - Part IV: "The Emotional Differences of the Sexes" See also Container OV 4, Handwritten drafts and notes, (4 folders) (Box 8)
        - Part IV: "The Emotional Differences of the Sexes", (1 folder) (Box 9)
      - Pagan Rites in Judaism, 1963 (Box 9)
        - Handwritten draft, (4 folders) (Box 9)
        - Typescript (Box 9)
      - Psychology of Sex Relations, introduction for a new edition, 1968 (Box 9)
    - German manuscripts, handwritten on large sheets, 1938-1941, undated See Container OV 5, same heading (Box 9)
    - Individual chapters or articles (Box 9)
      - "Comparative Psychology of the Sexes on the Street," undated (Box 9)
      - "The Courage of a Coward," undated See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - "An Experimenter and His Audience," undated See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - Freud, Sigmund, letters to Reik, transcriptions and English translations, 1911-1938, 1952 See also Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - "Guilt Feelings," undated See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - "A Holy Nation," undated (Box 9)
      - Partial draft on Anatole France's The Juggler of Notre Dame, undated (Box 9)
      - "Sexual Psychology in an American Novel," undated See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - "Some Traits of Feminine Sexuality," undated See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
    - Insertions ("einschub"), undated (Box 9)
    - Introductions to works by others, 1958, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Newspaper and magazine articles, 1913-1961 (Box 9)
      - Originals See Container OV 6, same heading (Box 9)
      - Photocopies, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Notebooks (Box 9)
      - English vocabulary, undated (Box 9)
      - Notes in German and English, undated (Box 9)
      - Notes on literature and philosophy, undated (Box 9)
    - Notes on (Box 9)
      - Freud, Sigmund, miscellaneous, undated (Box 9)
      - Judaism (Box 9)
        - Set 1, from Jewish Wit, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9)
        - Set 1, from Jewish Wit, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10)
        - Set 2, largely from Mystery on the Mountain, undated, (9 folders) (Box 10)